so probably the most famous book in all
of Buddhism is called the heart Sutra in
uh in in China it's called Shin Jing uh
in tibetan it's
called Uh and in that in that book they
teach about
emptiness in the in the heart then many
people ask me uh what is emptiness and
can you could you explain to me
emptiness in like 2 minutes you know I
can do that uh it takes about uh 20
years to learn it but I think you can
explain it in two minutes I like to do
it with a pen uh so I have this thing if
I hold this thing up to you and I say uh
what is this thing and then naturally
you will say oh this is a pen right and
then a if a dog came in the room and and
he came up to me uh here on the floor
and and he he jumped on the couch and
and I I showed him the pen uh then his
reaction to the pen would be to try to
bite it if he was a young puppy he would
try to bite it so we can say that the
puppy doesn't see a a pen the P the
puppy sees something to chew on right
and then if I ask you uh who's right you
see uh is the is the puppy right or is
the person right is it a pen or is it a
chew toy then people sit there for a
minute and then they say I think it's
both I think I think the puppy's right
and I think the human is Right different
different creatures see the thing as a
different thing so both of them are
right you can't say one of them is wrong
and one of them is right it's both this
object is a pen and it's also something
to chew on then we come to the next
question you see so what if I put this
pen down on the couch right and uh we
leave it there and then all the people
leave the room and all the dogs leave
the room and then I ask you well at that
time
once everybody has left uh then what is
this thing is it a pen or is it a CH toy
if I ask you choose which one it is is
it a pen which one of the two is it you
see and then your mind I think
everyone's mind correctly goes the idea
well it's neither at that moment it's
not a it's not a pen and at that moment
it's not a che toy if there's nobody
watching it and nobody to decide what it
is then um I think you can say that that
thing is is neither so really you came
up with what uh Nar came up with he said
uh this is a
pen this is a chw toy this is both a pen
and a chw toy and this is neither a pen
nor a CH toy you see theara came up with
this idea and it's not crazy right to
the human it's a pen uh to the dog it's
a
Choy uh if you ask who's right you have
to say Well they're both right and then
if all the dogs and the humans leave and
you put the thing here then you can say
it's neither one when you say neither
one that's emptiness okay that's the
meaning of emptiness and you can think
of emptiness like a uh movie screen I
like to think of it like a a blank white
movie screen okay at when you place the
object here and there's nobody looking
at it by itself from its own side it's
not a pen and it's not something to chew
on and that's emptiness uh now the
important step comes I think you have to
say well what good does that do me okay
if I understand that this thing isn't a
pen from its own side and I understand
that it's not something to chew on from
its own side if if I understand that
it's neither one by itself by itself
it's neither one it's nothing it's empty
it's blank then what good does that do
me you see how how is that going to make
me happy how is that going to help me
help make the world happy you see and
then you have to go on uh to a different
subject which is uh how do you make the
pen how do you make this object into
what you want it to be and how do you
make your life into what you want it to
be by using emptiness and that's a
different subject and we'll cover that
later